All right good afternoon everybody
各位同学，下午好
Welcome to see you
很高兴见到你们
So today we're going to look at an idea called exceptional control flow
今天我们要看一个叫做异常控制流的想法
That's a very important part of making modern systems
它是现代系统一个重要组成的部分
And it exists at all levels of the system from the lowest level hardware,all the way up to software
它存在于操作系统的各个层次，从最底层的硬件，直到软件
So the idea is when you turn on a computer (from the very) from the very first time you turn it on
当你从(第第)第一次打开计算机时，在你第一次开机的时候
On it just does execute one instruction after another until that you turn it off
它只是执行一个接一个的指令，直到你关闭计算机
Okay and if each core if you have multiple cores then each of those cores are executing instructions one after the other
好吧，如果每个核心，如果你的计算机有多个 cpu 核心，那么每个核心都会依次执行指令
Now the sequence of instructions is called the control flow
现在，指令序列称为控制流
Okay and the actual sequence of instructions that the hardware is executing is called the physical control flow
硬件正在执行的实际指令序列称为物理控制流
Now normally
现在通常
Normally,this control flow that executes just one instruction after another just sequentially in memory
通常，此控制流仅在内存中按顺序执行单条指令
And we've so far we've seen two mechanisms for altering the control flow
到目前为止，我们已经看到了两种改变控制流的机制
So that it's not
事实不是如此，
So that we're not executing just the next instruction
这样，我们可以不仅仅只是执行下一条指令了
So that's branches and jumps and procedure call and return
这就是「分支和跳转」以及「过程调用和返回」
Okay now jumps and call... branches jumps call and return
现在跳转并调用...分支跳转调用然后返回
Those are reacting to changes in program state
这些都是对程序状态变化的处理
So when you do a branch you check the control condition codes
当你执行分支时，请检查条件控制代码
And then based on some the results of that comparison then you do the branch
然后基于该比较的一些结果，然后你做相应的分支处理
Okay but its real system needs to be able to adapt to changes in the system state
好吧，但真正的操作系统需要能够处理系统级别的变化
Okay so for example data arrives from a disk
例如数据从磁盘到达
Or some network use types Ctrl-C
或者某些网络使用 Ctrl-C 类型中断
Okay the program executes an illegal instruction
还有，程序执行了非法指令
Okay all of these represent some change, some kind of change in the system state
所有这些代表了一些变化，系统状态的某种变化
And we need some way to react to that
于是，我们需要一些方法来对此做出反应
So this...
这...
So what we need is we call this exceptional control flow
我们需要的是称之为「异常控制流」的机制
Because it's sort of outside of the normal control flow that we see in our programs
因为它超出了我们在程序中看到的正常控制进程
Now exceptional control flow(ECF) exists at all levels in the system
现在，系统中的所有级别都存在「异常控制流（ECF）」
From the very lowest level of hardware
从最底层的硬件
At the very lowest level we have what are called exceptions
在最底层，我们有所谓的「异常」
And these are changes in the control flow in response to some low level system event
这些是响应某些底层系统事件的控制流的变化
So this is a...or and by event we mean a change in the state
这是...或者我们指的是事件引起状态的变化
Now exceptions are implemented using a combination of hardware and OS software which we'll see in it in a minute
现在使用硬件和操作系统软件的组合实现异常，等一会儿我们将会看到它们
But these exceptional control flow exists at higher levels too
但这些异常控制流也存在于更高的层次
So in the a process context switch is an example of exceptional control flow
在一个进程中，「上下文切换」就是是一个异常控制流程的典型示例
That's also it's implemented by a hardware and the operating system kernel
这也是由硬件和操作系统内核共同实现的
And it so a process context switches we'll see later later today
这样一个进程上下文切换，我们将在待会晚些时候看到
You're executing your code in the current in your current process
你正在当前进程中执行当前代码
And then all of a sudden this the system is executing code from another process
然后突然之间，系统正在执行另一个进程的代码
Right so your process gets like suspended
是的，你的进程就像暂停了一样
And so there's a...so that's a form of exceptional control flow
有一个...这是一种异常控制流
Where you're executing statements instructions within one process
你在一个进程中执行语句指令的位置
And then all of a sudden you're executing statements instructions in another process
然后你突然在另一个进程中执行语句指令
At a higher level are totally in software
在更高的层次上完全是软件
We have the idea of a signal
我们有一个「信号」的定义
And this is implemented by operating system software and we'll learn all about signals next lecture
这是通过操作系统软件实现的，我们将在下一讲中学习所有关于信号的知识
And then even higher,at an even higher level you have nonlocal jumps in C
然后甚至更高，在更高的水平，你有 C 的「非本地跳转」
Which are just implemented by the C run library
这些只是由 C 运行库实现的
So this allows you nonlocal jumps allow you to break the normal call and return pattern
这允许你非本地跳转，允许你打破正常的调用和返回模式
So from one...
从一个......
So from within a function normally you can only return to the function that calls that called you
在一个函数中，通常你只能返回到那个调用你的函数
Nonlocal jumps allow you to within a function break that and return to some other function or some other part of the code
非本地跳转允许你在函数中断并返回到某些其他函数或代码的其他部分
So we'll look at signals and nonlocal jumps next lecture
我们将在下一章讲述信号和非本地跳跃
Today we're going to look at exceptions and processes
今天我们将看看异常和进程
So an exception is a transfer of control to the operating systems kernel
一个异常是将控制权转移到操作系统内核
Where the kernel is the memory resident part of the operating system you know
内核是你知道的操作系统的内存驻留部分
So an operating system provides all kinds of programs like to list files,to change directories,to list the current processes
操作系统提供各种程序，如列出文件，更改目录，列出当前进程
So all of that stuff constitutes the operating system
所有这些构成了操作系统
The kernel is the part of the operating system that's always resident in memory
内核是操作系统中始终驻留在内存中的一部分
So an exception is really low-level transfer of control to the operating system
异常实际上是将低级别的控制权转移到操作系统
Because something happened in the system
因为系统中发生了一些情况
So you're executing your code,user code
而你正在执行代码，用户代码
And then something happens some event, so by event we mean there's some change in the system state
然后一些情况发生在某些「事件」上，我们称为事件引起了系统状态的一些变化
In response to that there the exception transfers control from your user code to code in the kernel
为此，异常将控制权从用户代码转移到内核态中的代码
Which is called an exception handler
这称为异常处理程序
And then the kernel responds to that change in some way
然后内核以某种方式响应这种变化
This is called the exception processing
这称为「异常处理」
And then there's three things that can happen after the kernel handles the exception
然后在内核处理异常后会发生三件事
It can return and reexecute that the current instruction
它可以返回并重新执行当前指令
Okay and we'll see this is useful for things like page faults allows us to implement virtual memory
我们会发现这对于「页缺失」这类允许我们实现虚拟内存的东西很有用
It could return to the next instruction
它可以返回到下一条指令
Which I've shown here or it could abort
这是我在这里展示的，也可能是中止的
Now exceptions are implemented by hardware and software
现在异常由硬件和软件共同实现
So the actual transfer of control
实际转移控制权
You know the change in the program counter or %rip is done by the hardware
你知道程序计数器或 %rip 的更改是由硬件完成的
But the code that executes as a result of that exception is set up and determined by the operating system kernel
但是由于该异常而执行的代码是由操作系统内核设置和确定的
So every type of event has a unique exception number
每种类型的事件都有一个唯一的「异常编号」
Which serves as an index into a jump table called an exception table
它用作跳转表的索引，称为异常表
Okay and so when event k happens
当事件 k 发生时
Then the hardware looks uses k as in as an index into this table
然后硬件使用 k 作为此表的索引
And gets the address of the exception handler for that exception
然后得到该异常的异常处理程序的地址
And so every time that event k happens that handler handler k is invoked
每次事件 k 发生时，都会调用处理程序处理程序 k
Now there's a different kinds of exceptions we distinguish them as being asynchronous or synchronous
现在有一种异常的分类方法，我们依此将它们区分为「异步」或「同步」
Asynchronous exceptions happen as a result of changes in state that are occurred outside of the processor
异步异常是由于处理器外部发生的状态变化而引起的
So these are called interrupts
这些被称为「中断」
And those changes in state are...
那些状态的变化是......
The processor is notified about those changes in state by setting a pin on the processor
通过在处理器上设置引脚，向处理器通知这些状态变化
An external pin called the interrupt pin
外部引脚称为中断引脚
So this is the kind of when see a disk controller finishes doing a direct memory access
这就是看到磁盘控制器完成「直接内存访问」的时候的情况
And copying data from the disk into memory
首先将数据从磁盘复制到内存中
It notifies the processor that it's finished that copy by setting the interrupt pin hi okay
它通过设置中断引脚来通知处理器它已完成复制
And so after an interrupt happens the handler returns to the next instruction
在发生中断后，处理程序返回到下一条指令
So an interrupt typically it's the so you're running your program,you're running your program and then there's like this little
一个中断通常是因为你正在运行你的程序，你正在运行你的程序然后就像这样，有一点点像
There's like this little pause while the interrupt handler runs and then your program just continues to run okay
当中断处理程序运行时，就像这个小暂停，然后你的程序继续运行正常
So it's usually sort of done behind the scenes and doesn't affect your execution of your program
它通常在幕后完成，不会影响你的程序执行
Now the most common...a common example of a interrupt is the timer interrupts
现在最常见的......中断的一个常见例子是定时器中断
So you're all systems have a built-in timer that goes off every few milliseconds
所有系统都有一个内置计时器，每隔几毫秒就会关闭一次
And when it,when the timer goes off it sets the interrupts pin high
当它，当定时器熄灭时，它将中断引脚设置为高电平
And there's a special exception number for timer interrupts
并且有一个特殊的异常编号用于定时器中断
And this is we need this in order for the
这就是我们需要这个以便
This allows we need this to allow the kernel to get control of the system again
这允许我们需要它来允许内核再次获得对系统的控制
Otherwise a user program could just run forever in an infinite loop
否则，用户程序可能会陷入无限循环中永远运行
And no one...there be no way for the operating system to get control
没有人......无法让操作系统获得控制权
So every few milliseconds this timer goes off that causes a transient exception into the kernel
此计时器每隔几毫秒就会关闭，从而导致内核发生瞬态异常
And then the kernel can...as we see the kernel can decide what to do
然后内核可以......正如我们所看到的，内核可以决定做什么
Maybe maybe schedule a new process or let the current process run
也许可以安排新进程或让当前进程运行
And then this an i/o interrupt from an external devices is also a common example
然后来自外部设备的这种 i/o 中断也是一个常见的例子
Now the other class of exceptions are synchronous exceptions
现在另一类异常是「同步异常」
And there are three classes of those
它有三类
One is that,one class is called the trap,a trap is a intentional exception
一个是，一类称之为「陷阱」，陷阱是故意的异常
So this is an exception that's caused intentionally by the program
这是一个由程序故意引起的异常
And the most common form of a trap is a system call
最常见的陷阱形式是「系统调用」
So you know the operating system kernel provides all kinds of services to a program
你知道操作系统内核为程序提供各种服务
But your program doesn't have direct access
但是你的程序没有直接访问权限
Your program can't call functions in the kernel,can't access data directly in the kernel
你的程序无法在内核中调用函数，无法直接在内核中访问数据
Because that memory is protected and unavailable to user programs
因为该内存受到保护且对用户程序不可用
So what the kernel does is they provide a interface that allows programs to make requests to effectively
内核的作用是提供一个允许程序发出请求的接口
Call functions within the kernel and to make requests for various services
调用内核中的函数并发出对各种服务的请求
And this interface is called a system call
此接口称为「系统调用」
Ok so a program makes a system call
一个程序进行系统调用
And requests various functions from the kernel
并从内核请求各种功能
The kernel provides those sort of reacts to that request
内核为该请求提供了对应的响应
And then returns control back to the the function there the calling program
然后将控制权返回给调用程序那里的函数
So you can think of a system call as kind of it's a...
你可以把系统调用想象成一种......
It looks like a function call but it's really transferring control into the kernel
它看起来像一个函数调用，但它却是将控制权转移到内核中
Okay then there's some so traps are intentional faults are unintentional but may be recoverable
好吧那么有一些陷阱是故意的，而一些故障是无意的，但可能是可以恢复的
Okay so things like page faults which
就像页缺失一样
When we will learn more about these when we study virtual memory
当我们研究虚拟内存时，我们将更多地了解这些内容
But something like a page fault it's actually recoverable
但是像页面错误这样的东西实际上是可以恢复的
It just that the kernel has to it means that the the data the portion of the address space that your program referenced isn't actually in memory
它只是内核，意味程序引用的一部分地址空间、数据部分实际上不在内存中
It needs to be copied from disk where it's stored into memory
它需要从磁盘复制到它应该存储在内存中的地址上
And then the instruction that that caused a fault needs is just restarted and then it works
接着，重新启动导致故障所需的指令，然后它就能正常工作
That the memory is there and then the instruction works properly
内存在那里，然后指令正常工作
But other faults are unrecoverable like protection fault
但其他故障是不可恢复的，如保护故障
So if you try to access a portion of memory that's not allocated
如果你尝试访问未分配的内存部分
Or floating-point exceptions often times those can be recoverable
或者通常是可以恢复的异常的浮点数异常
So in either case when there's a fault it either re-execute the current instruction all the abort
在任何一种情况下，当出现故障时，要么重新执行当前指令，要么全部中止
And then there's unintentional and unrecoverable exceptions which are called the aborts and those those always abort
然后是无意和不可恢复的异常，称为「中止」和那些总是中止的异常
So if you execute an illegal instruction,if there's a problem with your memory,memory and it's it's corrupted
如果你执行非法指令，如果你的内存存在问题，那么它就会被破坏
There's some problem with the machine those creative warts that always...
机器存在一些问题，那些创造性的总是......
That are unrecoverable and never return back to the program
这是不可恢复的，永远不会回到该程序
Now system calls there's...
现在系统调用那里......
Many different kinds of system calls and they all have their own unique number
许多不同类型的系统调用都有自己唯一的编号
Which is assigned by Linux
这是由 Linux 分配的
So for example to read a file,there's a system call called read
例如，为了读取文件，有一个名为 read 的系统调用
Which is number 0 opening a file, a system call number 2 and so on
这是编号0：打开文件，系统调用编码 2 等等
And there's an instruction called syscall
并且有一个名为 syscall 的指令
Which actually performs the system call
实际执行系统调用
Now you usually don't use this system call and strike the syscall instruction directly in your program the
现在你通常不需要在你自己的程序中直接使用此系统调用，并触发 syscall 指令
Linux wraps those in system level functions which actually call it for you
Linux 将这些函数包装在系统级函数中，这些函数实际上会为你调用的
But it's interesting in C how it actually works
但它在 C 中的实际工作方式很有意思
So opposed you want to open a file you call the system level function called open
假设你想打开一个文件，你调用称为 open 的系统级函数
With a file name and some options say read only write only
使用文件名和一些选项指定为 ：只读写
And so in at the syscall instruction takes the first the syscall number is %rax
在syscall指令中，第一个系统调用编号是 %rax
And then other arguments are %rdi,%rsi,%rdx, %r10, %r9, %r8
然后其他参数是 ％rdi，％rsi，％rdx，％r10，％r9，％r8
So you can see if we look in the the open function calls the __open function which actually invokes
你可以看看，我们是否在open函数中调用实际调用的__open函数
The syscall so if you look at that code you see it moves the 0x2
系统调用，如果你查看该代码，你会看到它移动0x2
which is the syscall number for read into %eax and then it does the syscall
这是读入 ％eax 的系统调用号，然后是系统调用
And then the the syscall returns its status in %rax
然后系统调用在 ％rax 中返回其状态
If it's a negative number then that means something some error occurred
如果它是负数，那么这意味着发生了一些错误
If it's a positive number then that means something that no error occurred
如果它是正数，那么这意味着没有发生错误
So in this case and in the open it's returning a file descriptor
在这种情况下，在 open 中它返回一个文件描述符
A small integer called the file descriptor which then you can use in subsequent calls to read and write
一个称为文件描述符的小整数，然后可以在后续的读写调用中使用
And then you can see the code is checking for this negative return value
然后你可以看到代码正在检查负的返回值
And there's a whole series of these compares
还有一系列的比较
So let's look at an example of a fault
那么让我们看一个故障的例子
So here suppose we have this program that we're writing into a valid region of memory
这里假设我们有这个程序，我们写入一个有效的内存区域
But it's not actually stored on...it's not actually in the memory,it needs to be loaded from disk into into memory
但它实际上并没有存储在......它实际上不在内存中，而是需要从磁盘加载到内存中
So this is a...so called page fault
这是......所谓的页缺少
So this instruction this movl
这个指令这个 movl
Because this because the memory at this address isn't available triggers a page fault
因为这是因为此地址的内存不可用，会触发页缺失
So that creates an exception a transfer of control into the the page fault handler in the kernel
这样就创建了一个异常，即将控制权转移到内核中的页缺失处理程序中
Which copies that page from disk to memory
哪个页面从磁盘复制到内存
And then it returns and when it returns it reacts acutes the movl instruction
然后它返回，当它返回时，它会对 movl 指令产生反应
So that's kind of cool
这很酷
So now the memory is available
现在可以使用内存了
And now that the movl this movl instruction when it's reacts acute completes
现在，当它的反应快速完成时，movl 这个 movl指令
And then we continue
然后我们继续
Now another type of fault is an invalid memory reference
现在另一种类型的故障是无效的内存引用
So here we have a...we're accessing an element of a
我们在这里......我们正在访问一个元素
Which doesn't exist and it's an illegal,it's an invalid reference
哪个不存在而且是非法的，这是一个无效的引用
So in this case the movl instruction
在这种情况下是 movl 指令
It looks like a...it looks like a page fault
它看起来像......它看起来像一个页缺失
But the kernel detects that it's an invalid address that there isn't anything that can be loaded from disk
但内核检测到它是一个无效的地址，没有任何东西可以从磁盘加载
This is an invalid region of the the virtual address space
这是虚拟地址空间的无效区域
So it sends a signal to the to the process and then never returns
它向进程发送信号，然后永远不会返回
So the signal that sends is the infamous segmentation
发送的信号是臭名昭著的部分
The signal that causes the infamous sauce segmentation fault message to print out
信号导致臭名昭著的酱汁？（此处字幕应有误） 并打印相关错误信息
And we'll see you next lecture,we'll see how these signals actually work
我们将在下一个讲座中看到你，我们将看到这些信号是如何工作的
Okay so I said we've seen exceptions or very low-level transfers of control
我说我们已经看到异常，或者非常低层的控制转移
That are implemented by both hardware and the operating system software...it could sue
这是由硬件和操作系统软件实现的...它可以
At the higher level is another form of exceptional control flow called
在更高层次上是另一种形式的异常控制流
And we see it in the context of a process context switch
我们在进程上下文切换中的上下文中看到它
So let's look at and let's look at what a process is
那么让我们来看看，让我们看一下进程是什么
So a process,the idea of a process is one of the most fundamental and important ideas in computer science
进程，进程的思想是计算机科学中最基本和最重要的思想之一
And this classical definition of is that a process is an instance of a running program
这个经典定义是，一个进程是一个正在运行的程序的实例
Okay it's different from a program
是的，它与程序不同
A program exists can exist in many different places right
存在的程序可以存在于许多不同的地方
A program exists in you save as text in a C file
你在 C 文件中以文本形式保存的程序
It can exist as the .text section of a binary
它可以作为二进制文件的 .text 部分存在
It can exist as bytes that have been loaded into memory
它可以作为已加载到内存中的字节存在
A process is an instance of a program that's running,that's in execution
进程是正在运行的程序的实例，正在执行中
And a process provides two key abstractions
进程提供了两个关键的抽象
Okay it's the first abstraction is that it gives it gives you the illusion that you have
好吧，第一个抽象就是，它给你带来的幻觉
Exclusive access to the CPU and registers
独占使用CPU和寄存器
Okay so when you're running
当你运行的时候
When you're running your program in a process
当你在一个进程中运行程序时
You never have to worry about any other programs modifying your registers
你永远不必担心其他程序修改你的寄存器
And you can't even tell that there's even other processes running on the system
而你甚至无法通知系统上还有其他进程在运行
Right it looks except for occasional delays like an instruction that just takes a little longer to run
它看起来很正常，除了偶尔的延迟，比如需要更长时间运行的指令
Except for that it looks like you have unique exclusive use of the of the processor and it's registers
除此之外，看起来你有独占的处理器和它的寄存器
The the other abstraction that it provides is the illusion that you have your own address space
它提供的另一个抽象是你拥有自己的地址空间的错觉
Okay so you have
你有
And this is provided by a mechanism called virtual memory
这是由一种称为虚拟内存的机制提供的
So each running program has its own code data heap stack
每个运行的程序都有自己的代码数据堆栈
And you never see that the code...
你永远不会看到代码......
And you never see the memory that's being used by other processes
而且你永远不会看到其他进程正在使用的内存
Okay so it looks for all intents and purposes process gives you this illusion that
它寻找所有意图和目的进程给你这种错觉
You have access to the exclusive access to all the memory and the and the processor
你可以访问所有内存和处理器的独占访问权限
Now that the system runs many of these processes simultaneously
现在系统同时运行了许多这些进程
Even on a system with a single core,many of these multiple processes are actually running at the same time concurrently
即使在具有单核的系统上，这些多个进程中的许多实际上是在同一时间并发运行
And you can see this if you look at this here I ran top on my mac
你可以看这个，如果你看到这里，我的Mac上顶部运行的
And you can see it's running 123 total processes, 5 of which are actually running
你可以看到它运行了123个进程，其中5个是处于实际运行状态
And each one of these processes has its own unique process id,this is integer
并且这些进程中的每一个都有自己唯一的进程ID，这是整数类型
Now the way so it looks like you have unique access or exclusive access to the system
现在看来你对系统有独特的访问权限或独占访问权限
But in reality on a suppose we have a single core on a you're actually sharing the system
但实际上，我们共享使用的系统其实只有一个核心
And the operating system is is sort of managing that sharing
操作系统就是管理共享
So what it does is it
它的作用是什么呢
We have a process that's running
我们有一个正在运行的进程
And it has its own...it has its own address space
它有自己的......它有自己的地址空间
And it has its own registers
它有自己的寄存器
And at some point either
在某些时候也是
Because...at some point an exception occurs either because of a timer interrupt
因为...在某些时候由于定时器中断而发生异常
Or a fault of some kind or a trap
或某种故障或陷阱
At some point the operating system gets control of the system
在某些时候，操作系统可以控制系统
And in this case let's say it decides that it wants to run another process
在这种情况下，让我们说它决定它想要运行另一个进程
So it copies the registers,the current register values into memory and saves them
它将寄存器，当前寄存器值复制到存储器中并保存它们
And then it schedules the next process for execution
然后它会安排下一个待执行的进程
And it loads the registers that were saved from the last time that process was running
并且它加载上次运行该进程时保存的寄存器
It loads those into the cpu registers
它将这些加载到 cpu 寄存器中
And then it switches the address space to the address space for this process
然后它将地址空间切换到此进程的地址空间
So this the address space and the register values are the context
这个地址空间和寄存器值是上下文
And so the context switch is what is the change in the address space and the registers
上下文切换是地址空间和寄存器的变化
Ok so then at that point the that process is running
那时那个进程正在运行
Now in reality on modern systems with multiple cores
现在实际上在具有多个核心的现代系统上
The operating system will schedule processes on those multiple cores
操作系统将在这些多核上安排进程
And then if there's not enough cores to handle the processes then it will do the context switching
然后，如果没有足够的核心来处理这些过程，那么它将进行上下文切换
Just like we showed before
就像我们之前展示的一样
Now each process represents a what we call a logical control flow
现在每个进程代表一个我们称之为逻辑控制流的东西
So if you were to you know there's a physical control flow
如果你对你知道有一个物理控制流
Which if we just looked at all the PC values
如果我们只看了所有的 PC 值，那该怎么办？
We'd be executing instructions from one process
我们将从一个进程执行指令
And then all of a sudden we'd be executing from another process
然后突然间我们将从另一个进程执行
But within a single process there's a logical control flow which are all the instructions for that process
但是在单个进程中，有一个逻辑控制流，它是该过程的所有指令
Now we say that two processes run concurrently
当它们的时序在时间上重叠时
If their flows overlap in time otherwise they're sequential
我们说两个进程同时运行（并发），否则它们是连续的
So let's look at an example we have three processes
那么让我们看一个例子，我们有三个进程
Process A runs for a while and then it's interrupted by process B and process C
进程A运行一段时间，然后被进程B和进程C中断
And then eventually it continues running and then it terminates
然后它最终继续运行然后终止
Process B interrupts process A and then it runs for a while and then it terminates
进程B中断进程A然后它运行一段时间然后它终止
Process C once when process B finishes then process C gets to run for a while
当进程 B 完成时，进程 C 进行一次，然后进程 C 运行一段时间
Then process A runs for a while and then process C terminates
然后进程A运行一段时间，然后进程C终止
Okay so given this definition of concurrency
给出了「并发」的这个定义
Which of these processes are running concurrently
哪些进程同时运行
What about a A and B?
A 和 B 怎么样？
So A and B flows, B's flow overlaps with A's flow right
有 A 和 B 两个逻辑流，B的逻辑流中断掉A的逻辑流
So B
B
B finishes starts and finish
B 完成开始和结束的一整个过程
Some portion this portion of B flow overlaps with A flow right
B 逻辑流的这部分的一部分与A逻辑流控制权重叠
Because B is still running hasn't finished
因为 B 还在运行还没有完成
Ok so A and B are concurrent as and similarly C and A overlap
A和B是并发的，并且类似地 C 和 A 重叠
So they're concurrent
他们是并发的
But B and C are not concurrent right B finishes before C starts
但是B和C在C不是并发的,因为 B 在 C 开始前完成
Now this idea of concurrency it doesn't
现在这种并发的概念并没有
This definition of concurrency holds regardless of the number of cores
无论核心数量为多少，这种并发性定义都会成立
Right even if you have one core this example that I showed you was on one core
即使你有一个核心，我向你展示的这个例子就是一个核心
But even if you have multiple cores as long as the flows overlap in time
但即使你有多个核心，只要逻辑流在时间上重叠
They're concurrent
那么他们是并发的
But we can think of these no matter what,we can think of these as running in parallel with each other
但是无论如何，我们都可以想到这些，我们可以认为它们是相互并行的
At least from the point of view of these individual processes
至少从这些个别的过程的角度来看
Now this notion of a context which
现在这个概念的上下文
It's managed by...its managed by the kernel
它由...由内核管理
Okay and it's important to realize that the kernel is not like a separate process that's running
重要的是要意识到内核不像是一个正在运行的独立进程
It always runs in the context of some existing process
它始终在某些现有进程的上下文中运行
And it's just code that's in the upper portion of the address space
它只是位于地址空间上部的代码
That gets executed as a result of an exception
这是因异常而执行的
So what what happens the way to think about this is that you have this process a that runs
那么考虑这个问题的方法就是你运行这个过程
And then an exception occurs which transfers control to the kernel
然后发生异常，将控制权返回到内核
The kernel invokes its scheduler which decides whether to let A continue to run
内核调用其调度程序，该调度程序决定是否让 A 继续运行
Or to to do a context switch and run a new process another process
或者做一个上下文切换并运行另一个新的进程
So in this example the scheduler is decided to run process B
在此示例中，调度程序决定运行进程 B.
So it executes code and then sort of changes sort of once it repoint the address space
一旦重新指定地址空间，它就会执行代码然后进行排序
Then it's running in the context of process B
然后它在进程B的上下文中运行
And it finishes loading the registers for process B general-purpose registers
它完成加载进程B通用寄存器
And then transfers control to B and B picks up where it left off
然后将控制权转移到 B ，和 B 从中断处继续
Okay
好的
And that at some point another exception occurs
而且在某些时候会发生另一个异常
And in the kernel decides to transfer control back to process A which picks up where it left off right here
并且在内核中决定将控制权转移回进程A，进程A在此处从中断处继续
So whatever instruction it finishes executing
无论它完成执行的任何指令
Whatever instruction was executing at the time of the exception execute the next instruction here
无论在异常时执行什么指令，都要执行下一条指令
Now Linux provides a number of functions
现在Linux提供了许多函数
You can call from a user program to manipulate processes
你可以从用户程序调用来操作进程
And this process this act of manipulating processes we refer to as process control
这个操作进程的过程我们称为进程控制
Now all of these functions,most I should say,most of these functions call invoke system, make system calls
现在所有这些函数，我应该说，大多数这些函数调用系统,进行系统调用
But they're wrapped in higher levels what we call system level functions that
但它们包含在我们称之为系统级函数的更高级别
That are the things you actually call from your user program
这是你实际从用户程序调用的内容
Now system level the Linux system level functions that will typically return -1 if there's an error
现在系统级，Linux系统级功能，如果出现错误，通常会返回-1
And then they'll set a global variable called error no to indicate the reason
然后他们将设置一个名为error no的全局变量来指示原因
So there's a hard and fast rule when you're doing
当你做的时候有一条硬性规则
When you're invoking system level functions
当你调用系统级函数时
You must check the return values from those functions you should
你必须检查应该使用的那些函数的返回值
And this you never you'll get into huge trouble
而你永远不会遇到麻烦
If you neglect to check the return values
如果忽略检查返回值
Okay so you should never make a system level function call without checking the return value
好吧，其实你不应该在不检查返回值的情况下，进行系统级函数调用
The and the only exception there's some functions that return void
唯一的例外是有些函数返回 void
Such as exit or free don't return anything
如 exit 或 free 不返回任何值
So the way the typical way you would do this is like the fork call
你这样做的典型方式就像 fork 调用一样
Which we use to create processes returns the process idea of the process that it created
我们用来创建进程的进程返回了它创建的进程的进程信息
Which is always positive if there's an error returns -1
则总是正数；如果有错误返回 -1，
So we check for the return value to be less than 0 and then we deal with that error somehow
我们检查返回值是否小于0，然后我们以某种方式处理该错误
Ok in this case we're just printing a message and exiting
在这种情况下，我们只是打印一条消息并退出
Now this gets although it's essential to do this it gets
现在，虽然这是必要的，但它必须这样做
From my point of view we're trying to present code to you
从我的角度来看，我们正试图向你展示代码
It gets really messy it takes up a lot of space
它变得非常混乱，占用了大量空间
Yes
是
[student speaking]
I'm checking that it's less than zero
我正在检查它是否小于零
Oh yeah that probably that should be normally the convention is to return non zero so you're right that
哦，是的，通常情况应该通常是返回非零，你是对的
It's not a hard and fast rule but that's typically the convention so I guess it should be exit one
这不是一个硬性规则，但这通常是惯例，我想它应该退出一个
So what we'll do to simplify this
那么我们要做些什么来简化这一点
In the code that we present to you and in the code that we present you in the book
在我们向你呈现的代码中以及我们在本书中向你展示的代码中
Well we'll define error reporting functions
那么我们将定义错误报告功能
So unix-style errors where the function returns -1 and then sets there error no
像 unix 样式的错误，其中函数返回-1然后设置错误号
Well if we get that kind of...if we get that kind of error will
好吧，如果我们得到那种......如果我们得到那种错误会
Will print the will print a message and we'll report what that error was  before we exit
将打印一条消息，我们将在退出之前报告该错误
And so then in the code we can replace that body of that if statement with just a single line
然后在代码中我们可以用一行替换if语句的主体
Okay so that makes the code a little tighter
这样可以使代码更紧凑
But we'll go even further than that and we'll define these wrappers
但我们会比这更进一步，我们将定义这些包装器
Which were pioneered by a great technical writer named W.Richards Stevens
这是由一位名叫『W.Richards Stevens』的伟大技术作家开创的
And what we do here is we replace each function with an error at a wrapper
我们在这里做的是在包装器中用错误替换每个函数
That has the identical interface as the function the original function
它具有与原始功能相同的界面
And it has the first,the first letter uppercase
它有第一个，第一个字母大写
And then what this wrapper does is it calls,it calls the original function checks for the errors
然后这个包装器做的是，它调用原始函数检查错误
And then if there's no error returns what the original function would have returned
然后，如果没有错误返回，原始函数将返回的内容
So the behavior of this wrapper is identical to the wrapped function
这个包装器的行为与包装函数相同
If there's not an error
如果没有错误
Okay and if there is an error then it deals with it somehow and prints a message
好吧，如果有错误，那么它以某种方式处理它并打印一条消息
And so then this allows us to make our code really compact without violating this
这使我们能够在不违反此规范的情况下使代码真正紧凑
Hard and fast rule that we have to check for errors
我们必须检查错误的硬性规则
Okay the simplest function process control functions are
最简单的功能过程控制功能是
Functions that allow you to get the pid for the current process which is getpid
getpid函数允许你获取当前进程的pid
Or the the processor idea of you if the parent process that created the current process
或者是处理器概念中的，创建当前进程的父进程
Okay so this these take no arguments and they return an integer which is a process id
这些不带参数，它们返回一个整数，这是一个进程ID
Now Linux provides ways to create and terminate processes
现在 Linux 提供了创建和终止进程的方法
And from a programmers perspective we can think of a process as being in one of three states running
从程序员的角度来看，我们可以将进程视为处于三种运行状态之一
So in this case the process is actually running and executes instructions
在这种情况下，该进程实际上正在运行并执行指令
Or it can be scheduled
或者它可以安排
Maybe it's not running but it can be scheduled at a later time
也许它没有运行但可以在稍后时间调度
And it's waiting is waiting to be scheduled
等待，等待被调度
It can be stopped which means that execution is suspended
它可以被停止，这意味着执行被暂停
And won't be scheduled until further notice
并且在进一步通知之前不会调度
So we'll see how this works when we study signals in the next lecture
当我们在下一讲课中研究信号时，我们将看到它是如何工作的
But usually a process is stopped because it receives a certain kind of signal
但通常一个进程会停止，是因为它会收到某种信号
And then that the process becomes stopped in ways it won't be executed
然后，该进程以不会被执行的方式停止
It won't be scheduled until you explicitly tell it to be scheduled
在你明确告知其调度之前，不会调度它
Or process can be terminated which means it stopped permanently
或者可以终止进程，这意味着它永久停止
Okay so it'll never be scheduled again it's done
它永远不会再被安排完成了
Now a process can be terminated for one of three reasons
现在可以通过三个原因之一终止进程
So one it receives a signal whose default action is to terminate it
它接收一个信号，其默认操作是终止它
Or your program returns from the main routine
或者你的程序从主程序返回
So you know you can...if you know the definition for main is int
你知道你可以...如果你知道 main 的定义类型是int
See main routines always return an int
看主程序总是返回一个 int
So you can return from main and that will terminate your
你可以从 main 返回，这将终止你的
Event it will terminate the process or you can explicitly call the exit function
事件它将终止进程，或者你可以显式调用 exit 函数
The exit function exits the program with an exit status of the of its argument
exit 函数退出程序，其退出状态为其参数
So as as you pointed out that the convention is that for normal return is to return 0
正如你所指出的那样，惯例是正常返回是返回0
And then nonzero on error
然后非零错误
Or you can...another way to do this is just return an integer value from the main routine
或者你可以...另一种方法是从主程序中返回一个整数值
And that will set the exit status
这将设置退出状态
Now exit is kind of unusual
现在退出有点不寻常
And you'll see this is typical of all these process control functions
你会发现这是所有这些进程控制功能的典型特征
That they normally functions you call them once and then they return once
它们通常起作用，你只调用一次，然后它们返回一次
Okay but exit you call once and then it never returns
但退出你一次，然后它永远不会返回
Okay so that's a little unusual
这有点不寻常
Now a parent process can create a child process by calling the fork function
现在，父进程可以通过调用 fork 函数来创建子进程
So fork takes no arguments
fork 没有参数
And it returns an integer,it creates a new child process
它返回一个整数，它创建一个新的子进程
And then it returns in both the parent and the child
然后它在父进程和子进程返回
So this is a little hard to wrap your head around at first
一开始，这有点难以理解
It's called once by the parent
它由父进程调用依次
But then it returns in both...it creates a new process and then it returns in both the parent and the child
但随后它返回...它创建一个新进程，然后它返回父进程和子进程
And to the child it returns 0
对于子进程，它返回0
To the parent return it returns to the child's process id
对于父进程返回，它返回子进程的id
Okay the child gets an identical copy of the parents virtual address space
子进程获得父进程虚拟地址空间的相同副本
But separate right there they're distinct
但在那里它们是截然不同的
But immediately after the fork returns the addresses the address space is identical
但是在 fork 返回地址之后，地址空间是相同的
So that means that all the variables,all the global variables the stack  the code
这意味着所有变量，全局变量，栈，代码
Everything is identical and the child it has the exact same values as it as it does in the parent
一切都是相同的，子进程与父进程一样具有完全相同的值
The child gets identical copies of the parents open open file descriptors
子进程获得父进程打开文件描述符的相同副本
So the child has access to any open files including like standard in and standard out that the parent had
子进程可以访问任何已打开的文件，包括父进程拥有的标准输入和标准输出
And the only difference is that the child gets a different process id than the parent
唯一的区别是子进程获得的进程ID与父进程不同
So fork is really strange
fork 很奇怪
Because it's called once,but returns twice once, in the parent and once in the child
因为它被调用一次，但返回两次，在父进程中返回，在子进程中也返回
So here's an example of this
这是一个例子
Here's...this is an example program, it has a local variable called x on the stack initialized to 1
这是......这是一个示例程序，它在堆栈上有一个名为 x 的局部变量，初始化为1
And then it calls fork and fork creates the child and returns a value to that both the parent and the child
然后调用 fork ，fork 创建子进程并向父进程和子进程返回一个值
The only way we can distinguish whether we're executing in the parent or the child is to check that return value
我们可以区分我们在父项或子项中执行的唯一方法是检查返回值
Okay so here if the process id if pid == 0
如果进程id为pid == 0
Then we're executing in the child
然后我们在子进程上执行
Now remember the child got exactly the same has exactly the same memory and encode is the parent
现在记住，子进程得到和父进程完全相同的内存和代码
So x in the child is 1
子进程的 x 是1
So when we print this message from the child,we increment x and then print this message
当我们从子进程打印此消息时，我们增加x然后打印此消息
So the child will print 1+1=2
子进程会打印 1 + 1 = 2
And then exit
然后退出
In the parent when we check that this process id
在父进程中我们检查此进程是否为 id
It's going to be nonzero because it's the process id of the child
它将是非零的，因为它是子进程的​​进程ID
So in this case...so the parent won't execute this the body of this conditional
在这种情况下......父进程不会执行这个条件的主体
So the parent will execute this printf
父级将执行此 printf
And in the parent we decrement x before we print it
在父进程中，我们在打印之前递减 x
So the parent prints out 1-1 is 0
父打印出的 1-1 是 0
Now there's no guarantee we have no guarantee whether the child or the parent executes first
现在无法保证，我们无法保证子进程或父进程是先执行
It could at when the fork
它可以在 fork 时
When the fork returns the kernel may decide to schedule the child first
当 fork 返回时，内核可能会决定先安排子进程
Okay in which case this code in the body of the conditional would run
在这种情况下，条件体中的代码将运行
Or it may decide to run the parent first okay
或者它可能决定首先运行父进程
And there's no way to predict and you it's is wrong,it's an error to make any assumption
并且没有办法预测，而且你，做出任何假设都是错误的
Like that about what's going to run first the parent of the child
关于子进程父进程，谁将先运行
And you can see that they share the same open files because
你可以看到他们共享相同的打开文件，因为
Both the parent and the child print to standard out and it prints on the terminal okay
父进程和子进程都打印到标准输出，它在终端上打印好了
Yes
是
Oh what if...the question is what if you call fork multiple times, I'll show you some examples of those
哦，如果......问题是如果你多次调用 fork，我将向你展示一些例子
It gets a little hairy will have...will use a model called the process graph to sort sort of understand what happens
它会有点难以理解......可以使用一个叫做进程图的模型来排序，理解会发生什么
Okay so like just like you said forks,forks can be kind of complex
好吧就像你说的 forks (叉子)一样，不过这把forks（叉子）可能有点复杂
And time to sin especially if they're nested or you call them multiple times
还有随着时间，特别是如果它们是嵌套的，或者你多次调用它们
So we use a tool called the process graph to capture sort of what could happen when we call forks
我们使用一种称为进程图的工具来捕捉我们调用 forks 时可能发生的情况
Right we can't make any assumption about the ordering of of different processes
对，我们不能对不同过程的排序做出任何假设
But we can capture the partial ordering of events using this tool called a process graph
但我们可以使用称为进程图的工具捕获事件的部分排序
So what we'll do is we'll let each vertex correspond to the execution of a statement
我们要做的是让每个顶点对应一个语句的执行
And then an edge is that happens before relation so a happens before b
然后边缘是在关系之前发生的， a 在 b 之前发生
And we will label edges with current values of variables
我们将使用当前变量值标记边
If we have a printf vertices
如果我们有一个 printf 顶点
A printed x that corresponds to a printf we can label that with the output
打印的 x 对应于printf，我们可以用输出标记
And then the every graph starts with a vertex with no edges
然后每个图形都以没有入边的顶点开始
So given this graph then any topological sort of the graph represents
给定此图，然后任何拓扑类型的图代表着
Some feasible total ordering of events
一些可行的事件总排序
And by topological sort we mean a total ordering of the vertices
通过拓扑排序，我们指的是顶点的总排序
Where all the edges go from left to right
所有边按照从左到右的顺序
Okay so let's look at how this would work for our example program
让我们来看看它如何适用于我们的示例程序
Here we have the parent initially x==1
这里我们的父进程最初是 x == 1
And then the parent calls fork
然后父级调用 fork
The fork returns in both the parent and the child
fork 在父级和子级中返回
The child prints...and both the parent and the child print the value of x  after incrementing or decrementing
子进程打印...父项和子项在递增或递减后均打印 x 的值
And then they both exit
然后他们都退出了
Ok so you can think of these
你可以想到这些
As happening...so these happen concurrently right which means they can be interleaved in any way the
正如所发生的......这些同时发生，这意味着它们可以以任何方式交错
So the topological sort of this graph will tell us a feasible
这个图的拓扑类型将告诉我们一个可行的
What's a feasible? What feasible inter leavings?
什么是可行的？什么可能的交错？
Okay so we can...so if we real able the graph just to keep it simple
我们可以...如果我们真的能够让图表保持简单
So if we real able these edges with just single letters
如果我们只用一个字母就可以实现这些边缘
Then this total ordering abecfd
然后这个总排序 abecfd
Represent is represents it's a topological sort and thus a feasible total ordering
Represent表示它是拓扑排序，是可行的总排序
So here we have a executing then b
这里我们使 a 执行然后 b
Then e execute in the child
然后 e 执行子进程
And then at this point the kernel decides to swap out,swap out e, swap out the child and now let the parent run
然后在这一点上，内核决定换出，换出e，换掉子进程，现在让父进程运行
So the parent picks up and executes c
父进程选择并执行c
And then it gets rescheduled to chat then the child gets scheduled and executes f
然后它被重新安排进行会话，然后子进程被安排并执行 f
And then the parent the parent runs and finally finishes
然后是父进程运行，最后完成
Right so this is very unlikely that
对，这是不太可能的
It you only execute one instruction and then b,and then have a context switch but it's it's feasible
它只执行一条指令然后执行 b，然后进行上下文切换，但这是可行的
Right because it represents
对，因为它代表了
Because the total ordering is a topological ordering
因为总排序是拓扑排序
On the other hand this is infeasible because f
另一方面，这是不可行的，因为 f
Here in this total ordering we're executing f before e
在这个总排序中，我们在e之前执行f
And you can see that this that just can't happen right
你可以看到，这是不可能发生的
So the edges on these the logical flow represented by this child
这些逻辑流上的边由它们的子进程表示
Have to occur in this order first e and then f right
必须先按此顺序发生 e 然后再向右进行
By the just because f follows e in the code right that the compilers not
仅仅因为 f 在代码中跟随 e 而编译器没有
Going to it's not going to alter those
它不会改变那些
Okay so what happens if now we have two consecutive forks
如果现在我们有两个连续的 forks 会发生什么
Well let's draw the process graph will help us understand this
那么让我们绘制流程图将有助于我们理解这一点
So in the parent we print L0  and then fork
在父进程中我们打印 L0 然后fork
And that creates a child and both
这创造了一个子进程，
And so the fork returns to this printf in both the parent and the child
fork在父级和子级中返回到此printf
So they both the parent and the child print L1
他们父进程和子进程都打印L1
And then both parent and child execute a fork
然后父和子都执行fork
So that creates another child,that creates two more,now two children
这样就创造了另一个子进程，创造了两个子进程，现在又创造了两个子进程
And then and so that returns to the printf which says bye
然后又返回到输出 bye 的 printf
So the result of this of calling fork twice like this is that it creates four processes
调用 fork 两次这样的结果是它创建了四个进程
And you can
你可以
And if it's confusing you can always work it out with the the process graph like this
如果它令人困惑，你可以随时使用这样的流程图
Okay so we can see feasible and infeasible orderings
我们可以看到可行和不可行的排序
So this one's feasible take my word for
这个可行我的意思
This one is infeasible
这个是不可行的
And let's see why so L0
让我们看看为什么 L0 如此
And there's no way to print by before the first fork
并且在第一个分叉之前没有办法打印
All right so that's infeasible
好吧，这是不可行的
If we drew out this process graph we'd have a backward edge
如果我们绘制出这个流程图，我们就会有一个后边
Okay now what happens if we nest forks in the parent
如果我们在父进程中嵌套 forks 会发生什么
Okay I'm not sure why you'd want to do this except maybe to torture 213 students
好吧，我不知道你为什么要这样做，除非想要折磨213名学生
But
但
So we can just work this out by drawing the process graph
我们可以通过绘制流程图来解决这个问题
So here we have the parent it prints L0
这里我们有父进程打印 L0
And then it does a fork so that creates a child
然后它做一个 fork ，以便创建一个子进程
So the child if fork is not equal to 0
子进程如果 fork 不等于0
Then we're in the parent right so this code executes in the parent
然后我们在父权限中，此代码在父进程中执行
If fork is 0
如果fork为0
Then we're executing the child and the child just prints by and then
然后我们正在执行子进程，子进程只是打印然后
And then terminate it eventually terminates I didn't show it here but  calls exit
然后终止它，最终终止我没有在这里显示，但是调用退出
Think the function that called this function calls exit
认为调用此函数的函数调用 exit
So the parent,so fork not equal to 0 indicates that this is the parent
父，fork不等于0表示这是父
So the parent prints L1 and then it does another fork
父进程打印L1，然后再做另一个fork
That fork creates a child
那个 fork 创造了一个子进程
So if fork is not equal to 0
如果 fork 不等于0
Then we're in the parent so the parent prints L2 and then exits this conditional and prints by
然后我们在父进程那里，父进程打印L2然后退出这个条件判断，并打印
If fork returns 0 then that means we're executing the child
如果 fork 返回0则表示我们正在执行子进程
So we don't execute this code we jump out of this conditional
我们不执行这个代码，我们跳出这个条件
And then the child just prints by
然后子进程就打印了
Okay
好的
And we can
我们可以
So this represents an infeasible output from this program
这代表了该计划的不可行输出
L0...
L0 ......
So L0 followed by bye, that's feasible
L0 跟着再见，这是可行的
And then followed by L1 that's okay
然后是 L1，那很好
And then the next bye is okay but it since
然后下一个 bye 是但从那以后
We can't have this...we can't have this by proceeding this L2
我们不能拥有这个...我们不能通过继续这个 L2
Because L2 will this printf will execute before this printf
因为L2将在此 printf 之前执行此 printf
Okay and I'll let you work out this one as an exercise
我会让你把这个作为练习
All right now when a process terminates for whatever reason
当一个进程因任何原因终止时，
The system actually keeps it around for until it's reaped
系统实际上一直保持它直到它被回收（reaped）
And the reason until it's reaped by its parent
直到它被父进程回收的原因
And the reason it does this is that the parent may want to know about the exit status of the child
它这样做的原因是父进程可能想知道子进程的退出状态
So but if a parent creates a child
但如果父进程创建一个子进程
It may want to wait for that child to finish and and check its exit status
它可能希望等待该子进程完成并检查其退出状态
So when any process terminates
当任何进程终止时
The system leaves that it, doesn't remove it entirely from the system
系统离开它，不会完全从系统中删除它
It keeps it a little bit of state associated with that child
它保持与该子进程相关的一点状态
In the form of a the exit status of the child
以子进程的退出状态的形式
And the in some other tables some other OS tables
在其他一些表中还有一些其他 OS 表
So because this child that's terminated but it's not gone
因为这个子进程已经终止但它并没有消失
It they're called zombies so there's sort of half half-living half-dead
它们被称为僵尸进程，半生半死
And so a process a zombie
这是一个僵尸的过程
Remains a zombie until it's reaped by its parent
仍然是一个僵尸，直到它的父进程回收
Using a function called wait or waitpid
使用名为 wait 或 waitpid 的函数
And as a result of doing wait or waitpid
并且由于 wait 或 waitpid
The parent is given the exit status information
父进程被给予退出状态信息
And then the kernel deletes the zombie process
然后内核删除僵尸进程
Now what if the parent doesn't reap it's one of its child zombies
如果父进程没有回收它的子进程僵尸，怎么办呢
So if any parent if the parent terminates
如果父节点终止，
Then the system arranges for the very first process that existed in the system
然后系统安排系统中存在的第一个进程
Called the init process which has a process id of one
进程ID为1的 init 进程
It arranges for the init process to reap that that child
它安排 init 进程回收那个子进程
So there's so orphaned children will always be reaped by the init process
初始进程总是会回收这样的孤儿进程
So we only really have to worry about reaping zombies
我们只需要担心回收僵尸
In the case where we have long-running parents like shells or servers
在我们有长期运行的父进程如shell或服务器的情况下
Because in that case a server may create millions of child processes
因为在这种情况下，服务器可能会创建数百万个子进程
Each one of those does...each one of those child processes when they terminate
每个子进程终止时都会执行这些进程
Become zombies and they have state
成为僵尸，他们有状态
That takes up room in the kernel so
这占用了内核的空间
You can get this it's a form of memory leak
你可以得到它，这是一种内存泄漏的形式
If you don't...if you don't reap these zombie children that can eventually fill up the memory space and crash the kernel
如果你不...如果你没有回收这些僵尸子进程，最终可能会填满内存空间并导致内核崩溃
So for cases where you have long-running programs
对于长期运行程序的情况
Then we have to use wait or waitpid to reap the children
然后我们必须使用 wait 或 waitpid 来回收子进程们
So let's look at an example,first let's look at an example of this zombie phenomenon
让我们看一个例子，首先让我们看看这个僵尸现象的一个例子
So here we have a function we call fork
这里有一个我们调用 fork 的函数
And then within the child we print a message of the process idea of that child and then we exit the child
然后在子进程中我们打印一个关于那个子进程的信息，然后我们退出子进程
Within the parent we print a message and then we go into an infinite loop
在父进程内我们打印一条消息，然后我们进入一个无限循环
Okay so this is a parent that's that never reaps the child that it created
这是一个永远不会回收它创建的子进程的父进程
So if we run this program called forks
如果我们运行这个调用 forks 的程序
You can see it prints these two messages
你可以看到它打印这两条消息
The parent prints a message and the child prints a message and then
父进程打印一条消息，然后子进程打印一条消息
And we're running it in the background with this ampersand
我们用这个 ＆ 符号在后台运行它
Okay because we're going to otherwise it would...it's still running
因为我们,不会这样......它还在运行
And we wouldn't be able to inspect it
我们无法检查它
So after we run this program in the background
在我们在后台运行这个程序之后
Then we use ps to print the current processes
然后我们使用 ps 来打印当前进程
And we can see that there's two...we can see here at the parent which is process id 6639
我们可以看到有两个......我们可以在父进程中看到进程ID为 6639
And then the child which is 6640 and
子进程是 6640和
That the defunct indicates that it's a zombie
那失效表明它是一个僵尸进程
Okay now if we kill 6639 that's the parent
如果我们杀死6639，那就是父进程
And then do another ps you see that the zombies gone that the child is gone
启动另一个ps，你看到那个僵尸进程消失了。子进程消失
Because it's been reaped by the init process one
因为它是由init进程获得的
Now what happens if the child doesn't terminate you might wonder like if a parent creates a child
现在如果子进程没有终止会发生什么，你可能想知道父进程是否创建了子进程
And then the parent,and then the child never terminates
父进程，然后子进程永远不会终止
And the parent terminates then what would happen right mark
父进程终止了正确的标记
So let's just let's look at an example of those in C
那么让我们来看看 C 中的例子
So here we're calling fork we're creating a child
我们在这里打电话给我们创造一个子进程
Within the child we'd print a message and then the child goes into an infinite loop
在子进程中我们打印一条消息，然后子进程进入无限循环
And the parent prints a message and then exits
父进程打印一条消息然后退出
So if we run this program
如果我们运行这个程序
You can see that the two messages from parent and child
你可以看到来自父级和子级的两条消息
And then if we look at the...if we look at the processes
如果我们看一下......如果我们看一下这些进程
We can see that the child is still running
我们可以看到子进程还在运行
Okay so the channel process is still running even though the parents's has terminated
即使父进程已经终止，管道进程仍然在运行
And now if we kill this child 6676
现在，如果我们杀死这个子进程 6676
And then if we kill it,then we can see that it's it's gone,it's no longer in the system okay so
如果我们杀了它，那么我们可以看到它已经消失了，它不再在系统中了，
That child when we killed it that terminated
那个子进程，当我们杀了它终止了
It it had no parents so the init process reaped it and it it's no longer a zombie
它没有父进程，初始进程回收了它，它不再是僵尸进程
So the function that we use to synchronize with children and reap them
我们用来与子进程同步并回收他们的函数
The simplest one is called wait
最简单的一个叫做 wait
And wait it takes an optional status
wait 它需要一个可选状态
Where you can get the exit status of ,the inspect the exit status of the child
在哪里可以获得检查子进程的退出状态
Basically wait suspends the execution of the process that calls it
基本上 wait 会暂停执行调用它的进程
Until one or one of its children terminates
直到一个或其中一个子进程终止
And it doesn't specify which one it just waits,until one of the children that it created terminates
并且它没有指定它只是等待哪一个，直到它创建的一个子进程终止
And then if this child status is not null
如果此子进程状态不为空
Then the integer that it returns or the integer that it points to this is a pointer
然后它返回的整数或它指向的整数是一个指针
The integer that it points to will be set to some value that indicated the reason the child terminated and its exit status
它指向的整数将被设置为某个值，该值指示子进程终止的原因及其退出状态
And you can check that using these macros
你可以检查使用这些宏
Which your textbook describes in more detail and let you
你的教科书将更详细地描述，并让你
So let's look at how this works in a simple example
让我们看一下这个工作原理的简单示例
So here we're calling fork and creating a child which prints a message and then exits
这里我们调用fork并创建一个打印消息然后退出的子进程
The parent prints a message and then it waits for the child to terminate
父进程打印一条消息，然后等待子进程终止
And when the child terminates it prints a message
当子进程终止时，它会打印一条消息
And indicating that the child terminated and then prints by
并指示子进程终止然后打印
So if we were to look at the process graph for this
如果我们要查看流程图
You would see that we would have the fork creates the parent and the child
你会看到我们会让fork创建父级和子级
Both the parent and the child do they're printf
父进程和子进程都会打印
And then the parent waits it suspends until that the child terminates in this case by calling exit
接着父进程等待它暂停，直到子进程在这种情况下通过调用exit终止
Okay so what that means is it's infeasible
那么这意味着它是不可行的
So you can say hello from the parent
你可以向父进程打招呼
It's infeasible though for this
尽管如此，这是不可行的
This child terminated message CT to occur before the bye
这个子进程在再见之前终止了消息 CT
Because
因为
Because the child hasn't yet terminated so
因为子进程还没有这样终止
It's these two...these two messages will never be printed
这是两个......这两个消息永远不会被打印出来
Until the child is terminated by calling exit
直到子进程通过调用 exit 退出终止
So is that clear yes
明确的是
So the question is can you have an output HP
问题是你有输出 HP 吗？
HP,HC,CT bye yes
HP，HC，CT再见
Yes because the parent prints HP, there's a context switch the child prints HC and then exits
是的，因为父进程打印HP，有一个上下文切换，子进程打印HC然后退出
And now the parent will the wait will return
现在父进程将等待返回
And then it prints CT bye
它打印 CT 再见
Okay here's this is a...this is a little more a little more involved example
这是一个...这是一个更多一点参与的例子
So here what we want to do we're going to create a bunch of children
我们想要做的就是创造一堆子进程
And then we're going to wait for them all to terminate
我们将等待他们全部终止
And we're going to wait but we won't be able to wait in any specific order right we're just...
我们将等待，但我们将无法按任何特定顺序等待，我们只是......
So here we have a loop 0 through n
这里我们有一个循环 0 到 n
And in each loop body we're going to fork a child and exit with a return status
在每个循环体中，我们将fork一个子进程，并带有一个返回状态退出
That that's going to tell us which child it was
这将告诉我们这是哪个子进程
In the parent so we do this n times
在父进程那里我们这样做了 n 次
And then afterward the parent inside a similar loop 0 to n
父进程在类似的循环 0 到 n 内
Add waits for a child to terminate
添加等待子进程终止
So it will wait for n children to terminate
它将等待n个子进程终止
Wait returns the the process id
等待返回进程ID
And then a status which is... in this child status variable
是这个子状态变量中的状态....
And so we take that variable now and we can use this w if exited macro to determine
我们现在采用该变量，如果退出宏，我们可以使用此 w 来确定
If it terminated normally with an exit by calling exit
如果它通过调用 exit 退出，正常终止
And if so then we can check its exit status using the WEXITSTATUS macro
如果是这样，那么我们可以使用 WEXITSTATUS宏 检查其退出状态
Otherwise if w exited it
否则，如果退出它
It's false then that means something the child terminated for some other reason not because it called exit
这是假的，这意味着子进程因某种其他原因而终止，而不是因为它调用exit
Okay there's a
有一个
We can actually use waitpid which is similar to wait
我们实际上可以使用类似于 wait 的 waitpid
But it allows us to wait for a specific process a specific child
但它允许我们等待特定进程，特定子进程
A specific child with a specific process id to terminate
以终止具有特定进程ID的特定子进程
And I'll let you can waitpid is really involved and
我会告诉你，waitpid真的可以参与其中
It's described in detail in your textbook
它在你的教科书中有详细描述
And so you'll need to look, you'll need to look there for the details on how that works
你需要查看，你需要查看有关其工作原理的详细信息
Now another important so we've learned how to create new processes
现在另一个重要的是，我们已经学会了如何创建新进程
The but we haven't learned how to when we call fork
但我们还没有学会如何调用 fork
We just create an exact copy of the child is just an exact copy of the parent
我们只是创建一个子进程的精确副本，只是父进程的精确副本
Running the same code,same program,same variables
运行相同的代码，相同的程序，相同的变量
Okay to run a different program inside of a process we use a function called execve
好吧，要在进程内运行不同的程序，我们使用一个名为 execve 的函数
And execve loads and runs
并执行加载和运行
Within the current process it loads and runs
在当前流程中，它会加载并运行
The executable file name which is its first argument
可执行文件名，这是它的第一个参数
And file name can be either a binary executable
文件名可以是二进制可执行
Okay or it can be a script,it can be a text file
好吧，或者它可以是一个脚本，它可以是一个文本文件
A so-called script file that starts
一个所谓的脚本文件启动
Whose first line starts with a pound bang and then that the path of some interpreter
谁的第一行以一声巨响开始，然后是一些解释器的路径
So for example if you want to write a shell script
例如，如果你想编写 shell 脚本
You the first line of your shell script is a pound bang and then
你的 shell 脚本的第一行是一个巨大的爆炸然后
The path name of the bash
bash 的路径名
And then that will execute bash
那将执行 bash
And then bash will read in that the lines following and interpret them
bash将读取下面的行并解译它们
As just as though you'd type them in at the command line
就像你在命令行输入它们一样
So in either case it executes either an interpreter or it executes a binary
在任何一种情况下，它都执行解释器，或执行二进制文件
With who's argued with the argument list argv
谁对于参数列表argv感到迷惑
And a list of environment very in envp
以及envp中的环境列表
Okay now by default are the first argument
现在默认是第一个参数
In argv is the name of the file that that's being executed so it's this file name
在 argv 中是正在执行的文件的名称，它是此文件名
So what that allows you to do is
那么你可以做的是
In your code you can check argv[0] if you want to print out the name of the file,the name of the program that's executing
在你的代码中，你可以检查argv [0]，如果你想打印出文件的名称，正在执行的程序的名称
You just print out argv[0]
你只需打印出argv [0]
Okay now and exits all of the code and the data and the stack
现在好了，退出所有代码，数据和堆栈
It overwrites the completely overrides the virtual address space
它会覆盖，完全覆盖虚拟地址空间
So once you call eggs a within a process
一旦你在一个进程调用eggs
It blows away the current program that's it
它打破了当前的程序
Okay however it retains that it's still the same process, it's just running now a different program
好吧但是它保留了它仍然是相同的进程，它现在只是运行一个不同的程序
And so it retains the process id and any open files that you have
它保留了进程ID和你拥有的任何打开文件
So execve is really mind-blowing because it's called once
execve真的令人兴奋，因为它被称为一次调用
But it never returns
但它永远不会返回
Except if there's an error
除非出现错误
So if this file doesn't exist for example then then exec will return on -1
如果此文件不存在，那么exec将返回-1
But otherwise in normal operation it never returns
但在正常操作中它永远不会返回
All right so let's look at the structure of the stack
让我们来看看堆栈的结构
When this new program starts so after
当这个新程序开始之后
After exit...after the egg argv finishes its work it creates
退出之后...在argv完成它的工作之后它创造了
It create a new stack, it loads in new code and data creates a new empty heap
它创建一个新的堆栈，它在新代码中加载数据，创建一个新的空堆
Ok everything's new
一切都是新的
And the stack that it creates has the following form
它创建的堆栈具有以下形式
Ok at the bottom here's the bottom of the stack and our stack is growing this way
好吧，在底部这里是堆栈的底部，我们的堆栈正在以这种方式增长
So the first function that executes
执行的第一个函数
Is a function called libc_start_main
是一个名为 libc_start_main 的函数
So that has a stack frame
它有一个堆栈框架
So let's look this is what I'm showing here is the situation right before the startup code calls main
让我们看看，这是我在这里展示的是，启动代码调用main之前的情况
So there's the future stack frame for main will be here at the top of this
main的未来堆栈框架将位于此顶部
Following the top of the stack
在堆栈顶部之后
There's some padding and then the argument list in argv  is contained on the stack
有一些填充，然后argv中的参数列表包含在堆栈中
So that the argv is a list of pointers terminated by the null pointer
这样argv就是一个由空指针终止的指针列表
And each one of these pointers points up into a string that corresponds to an argument
这些指针中的每一个都指向一个与参数对应的字符串
Okay so when you run a program you specify the program name
在运行程序时指定程序名称
And then arguments separated by spaces
由空格分隔的参数
Okay and so these arguments this argv is a list of pointers to those arguments strings
这些参数，这个argv是一个指向这些参数字符串的指针列表
And it's pointed to right as main is called
它被指向 main 被调用的地址
It's the second argument to main
这是 main 的第二个参数
So it's contained in %rsi the address of this argument lists
它包含在 ％rsi ，这个参数的地址列表
The number of arguments is contained is the first argument argc
第一个参数argc是包含的参数数量
And that's contained in %rdi by the x86-64  parameter passing convention
并且 x86-64 参数传递约定包含在 ％rdi 中
Now the environment list is also contained on the stack
现在，环境列表也包含在堆栈中
And it too consists of a list of pointers each of which points into a environment string
它也包含一个指针列表，每个指针都指向一个环境字符串
Which is a set of key equal value pairs, okay
哪一组是关键的等值对,好的
And it's pointed to by the global environment variable environ
全局环境变量指向了它
And if it's passed in it's pointed at an envp it which is contained in %rdx
如果它被传入，则指向包含在 ％rdx 中的envp
Which is the always holds the third argument
这就是总是存在的第三个参数
Okay so let's look now how we would use this
现在让我们来看看我们将如何使用它
So we want to within our current program we want to execute the ls command
我们希望在当前程序中执行 ls 命令
With two arguments - lt and /usr/include
有两个参数 -lt 和 /usr/include
So what this is saying is list,list the files in /usr/include
这就是list，列出/usr/include中的文件
Show the long form of the listing and sort them in time order
显示list的长格式并按时间顺序对其进行排序
From most recently used to at least recently used
从最近使用到最少最近使用过
So the way we do this
我们这样做的方式
If we just called execve it blow away our program
如果我们只是调用 execve，那就吹走了我们的程序
So assuming we want to continue to do work after we execute ls
假设我们想在执行ls后继续工作
The the standard way to do this is to to create a child using fork
执行此操作的标准方法是使用fork创建子进程
And then x act within the child
x在子进程内行动
Right have the child do the work
是的，让子进程工作良好
And then the child terminates and the parent maybe will wait for the child, maybe not right just
子进程终止，父进程可能会等待子进程，可能不对
Usually it will wait for the child
通常它会等待子进程
So within the parent we fork a child check that it's 0
在父进程中，我们 fork 子进程检查它是 0
And so if it's 0 then we're executing that this code executes within the child
如果它为0，那么我在子进程中执行这段代码
So the child does the exact
子进程恰好工作
It passes the name of the function since the
它传递了函数的名称
The name of the function that we want to the program that we want to execute
我们想要执行的程序的函数名称
Is always contained in the first element of argv
始终包含在 argv 的第一个元素中
We call exit with a parameter of myargv[0]
我们用参数 myargv [0]调用exit
And we've set up the argument list in myargv
我们在 myargv 中设置了参数列表
And we pass the global environment variable environment
我们传递了全局环境，变量环境
We're just going to use the current list of environment variables that we have in the parent
我们将使用父进程中的当前环境变量列表
Okay and these environment variables are things of the form USER=droh current working directory
这些环境变量是USER = droh，当前工作目录的形式
And so the the...
......
If this program in myargv[0] doesn't exist then exact will return -0
如果myargv [0]中的这个程序不存在，那么exact将返回-0
So we check for that condition and then exit
我们检查那个条件然后退出
Otherwise it never returns right it executes ls
否则它永远不会返回，它执行ls
ls the code for ls
是 ls 的代码
This is the name of a binary this is a /bin/ls is a binary file
这是二进制文件的名称，这是/bin/ls，它是二进制文件
That binary file gets loaded into memory
该二进制文件被加载到内存中
That code gets executed and it terminates
该代码被执行并终止
Okay so the child at this point after the exit
在子进程在退出后的这一刻
The child is running that the ls code
子进程正在运行ls代码
And it's no longer running any of this code
并且它不再运行任何代码
Now this seems the first time you see this combination of fork and exec it seems a little odd doesn't it
现在这似乎是你第一次看到这个 fork 和 exec 的组合，看起来有点奇怪不是吗
why not just
为什么不呢
Why not just have one command that creates a new process and runs
为什么不只有一个命令来创建一个新进程并运行
And runs a program in that process ，why
并在该过程中运行程序，为什么
Why separate why have these two separate fork and exec
为什么要分开这两个单独的fork和exec
I mean in fact windows does this windows has like one command that creates a process and executes
我的意思是事实上，windows这个窗口就像一个创建进程并执行的命令
But it turns out that having a separate function like fork
但事实证明，拥有像fork这样的独立功能
Just to create processes is actually really useful
仅仅创建流程实际上就已经非常有用
I mean sometimes you just want to create replicas of your current process for example
我的意思是有时你只想创建当前进程的副本
Let's say you have a server
假设你有一台服务器
And you want to create a concurrent server you want to create multiple copies of that server then you just fork
并且你想创建一个并发服务器，你想要创建该服务器的多个副本，然后你只需要 fork
A bunch you have the main the parent server can fork a bunch of children
你的主服务器的一堆父服务器可以fork一堆子进程
So that's useful they're just all running the same code
这很有用，他们只是运行相同的代码
But what's all...what this also allows you to do
但是这一切......这也让你做到了
Is it allows you to execute code in the child
是否允许你在子进程中执行代码
Before you call execve
在你调用execve之前
So you may want to set some,you may want to set some...
你可能想设置一些，你可能想设置一些......
Like some signal with is especially useful when you're dealing with
在你处理时，一些信号就特别有用
With things like signals if you want to block certain signals or unblock certain signals
如果你可以阻塞某些信号或打开某些信号
You can do it right here in this this gap between the fork and the exact
你可以在这个fork和精确的间隙中做到这一点
Okay so that's it so just to summarize what we've talked about today
总结我们今天谈到的内容
Exceptions are in response to events that require some kind of non-standard or exceptional call exceptional control flow
异常是对需要某种非标准或特殊调用异常控制流的事件的响应
They can be generated internally in the form of interrupts or internally in the form of traps and faults
它们可以以中断的形式在内部生成，也可以以陷阱和故障的形式在内部生成
So at any point in time a process has multiple a system as multiple processes
在任何时间点，进程都有多个系统作为多个进程
Only one of which can execute on a single core
其中只有一个可以在单个核心上执行
So the process execution is interleaved by the kernel
由内核交替执行进程
And each process thinks that it has total control of the processor in its address space
并且每个进程都认为它在地址空间中完全控制了处理器
There's only one mechanism to spawn processes that's fork
只有一种机制来生成的进程，那就是 fork
And it's called once and returns twice
它被调用一次并返回两次
We can terminate our process by calling exit which is called once and never returns
我们可以通过调用一次调用exit来终止我们的进程，并且永远不会返回
We reap and wait for processes using wait or waitpid
我们可以使用wait和waitpid回收并等待进程
And we load and run programs using execve
我们使用execve加载和运行程序
Or one of its one of its variants
或者它的一个参数之一
And this one is called once and and normally never returns
这个被称为调用一次，从不返回
Okay so that's it for today and
这就是今天的全部内容
We'll see you have a good weekend and we'll see you on Tuesday
祝你们周末愉快，周二我们再见